Hello, today's דף Daf is ק, Kuf, 100. So you all deserve
a pat on the back for having gone through 100 דפים Dapim
of חולין. Chullin.
And 99... good point. And today is the last דף Daf for
a little while till we get to the next פרק Perek about
intensive כשרות Kashrus stuff. So just because we're talking about גיד הנשה,
Gid HaNasheh, remember that's our פרק, Perek, and we talked about what
happens if you forgot and cooked your גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh with
the chunk of meat, we had a very intensive discussion about the
whole idea of taste and sixty, that will end after the first
עמוד Amud today, and we only will revisit כשרות Kashrus when we
get to the next פרק. Perek. Okay, let's take a look. But
we still have a very important גמרא Gemara yet to go. And
that is, if you remember, the משנה Mishnah said that until now
we've been talking about how to determine taste and מין במינו, min
be-mino, מין באינו מינו, min be-eino mino, the model of sixty, ask
a non-Jew, etc. The משנה Mishnah also said though, if this גיד
gid was cooked with other גידים, gidim, and you can't identify it,
you can't eat anything. Or if a chunk of non-kosher meat or
a piece of non-kosher fish was cooked with other chunks of meat
and you can't identify it, you can't eat any of it. And
that suggests that
when you're not dealing with just taste, when you're actually dealing with
the thing itself and it can't be removed, that it is not
בטל. batel. And that certainly sounds that way very much from the
משנה. Mishnah. The גמרא Gemara pushes back on this, because the גמרא's
Gemara principle is that ביטול bitul works not only to negate taste,
but it actually works to negate the thing itself. Okay, that's something
that we do know is well-established from other places. Not only that,
maybe you would have distinguished between, it's one thing if something gets
mixed up and is equally dispersed. Imagine for example, like משניות Mishnayos
we had in קדשים, Kodashim, blood gets mixed up with water, blood
gets in wine, so it's not just the taste, it's the thing
itself. But there you can understand that it loses its identity, right,
because it all gets dispersed, it all becomes one big mixture. But
if you have a chunk of meat and other chunks of meat,
or a גיד gid and other גידים, gidim, you could say not
only is the thing itself there, but it retains its integrity, it
retains its identity, right, as separate pieces. Maybe ביטול bitul shouldn't work.
How do you say the thing stops existing? Each piece is independent.
So the simple sense of our משנה Mishnah is that ביטול bitul
does not work in that case. That is called a case of,
until now you've been introduced to concepts of מין במינו, min be-mino,
like and like, apples and apples, and מין באינו מינו, min be-eino
mino, unlike, apples and oranges. That's what matters most in terms of
taste. Now we're being introduced to a new category called by the
ראשונים, Rishonim, not explicitly by the גמרא, Gemara, as יבש ביבש, yavash
be-yavash, dry and dry, as opposed to לח בלח, lach be-lach, liquid
and liquid. The idea of that is not literally liquid or dry,
the idea is is it a type of mixture in which everything
becomes a homogeneous mass? If you turned everything into your blender and
you run it through your blender and you turned it all into
some type of mush, that's also liquid, because everything is a homogeneous
mass. Or do things retain their indistinct identity? יבש ביבש. yavash be-yavash.
And the simple sense of our משנה Mishnah is if you have
one chunk of non-kosher meat, other chunks of kosher, one גיד gid
and other גידים, gidim, that because each thing retains its identity, it
does not get mixed up and ביטול bitul does not work. If
you can't identify it, throw it all out. But the גמרא Gemara
pushes back on that, and the גמרא Gemara assumes that ביטול, bitul,
nullification, works even in cases of יבש ביבש yavash be-yavash and therefore
reinterprets the case of the משנה. Mishnah. I'll take your questions in
a minute, let's just read the two lines in the גמרא Gemara
that do this to both cases in the משנה, Mishnah, and then
we'll take your question. So very last line on צט עמוד ב,
Tzadi Tes Amud Beis, גיד
הנשה שנתבשל, gid ha-nasheh she-nisbashel, so this is the גיד gid is
mixed up with other גידים, gidim, so the גמרא Gemara says in
two very powerful words, וליבטל ברובא. u-livatel be-rubah. Let it become בטל
batel by a majority. Okay, so what if they're all יבש ביבש,
yavash be-yavash, distinct objects? ביטול, bitul, nullification, should work even when it's
not a homogeneous mass, and if the majority is kosher, that should
nullify the minority. And maybe here even taste doesn't matter, because you're
not mixed up together. So therefore even majority should be enough. So
the גמרא's Gemara answer to this is בריה שאני. beryah shani. Like
amazing four words here in the גמרא. Gemara. First the גמרא Gemara
completely rejects the assumption of the משנה, Mishnah, ביטול bitul should work
even in this case. And the answer is with two words. Yes,
you're right, ביטול bitul does work even by יבש ביבש, yavash be-yavash,
even by distinct objects. Why does it not work in the משנה?
Mishnah? Because the גיד gid is a בריה. beryah. Remember we introduced
the idea that if you eat a גיד הנשה, gid ha-nasheh, even
if it doesn't have a כזית, k-zayis, you get lashes, because it
is a whole object. It has entire, the גיד gid has its
distinct identity. Now that would only be if you cooked the entire
גיד. gid. According to this, if you cooked a segment of the
גיד, gid, it would be בטל. batel. But if you cooked the
entire גיד, gid, because that has significance, it's the whole thing that
the תורה Torah forbade, therefore it cannot be negated, its significance prevents
it from losing its identity from being negated. Okay, let's read one
other case, the other case in the משנה, Mishnah, and see the
answer to that. Top of ק עמוד א, Kuf Amud Aleph, וכן
חתיכה של נבילה, ve-chen chatichah shel neveilah, a chunk of נבילה... neveilah...
top of ק ע"א, Kuf Amud Aleph, וכן חתיכה של נבלה, v'chein
chaticha shel neveilah, a chunk of non-kosher meat, non-shechted meat mixed up
with other shechted meat. It says if you can't identify it, can't
eat any of the meat. So the גמרא Gemara rejects the assumption
and says again in two words, ותבטל ברוב, v'tibatel berov, let it
become בטל batel with a majority. And the answer is, notice the
difference, ליבטל libatel and תבטל, tibatel, I think one's masculine, feminine. Anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara answers, one minute, I have an answer. הניחא
למאן דאמר כל שדרכו למנות שנינו. hani'cha l'man d'amar kol shedarko limnot
shaninu. It makes sense according to the opinion that says the text
in the משנה, Mishna, there's a fascinating debate of רבי יוחנן Rabi
Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish based on the text of a
משנה. Mishna. There is a משנה Mishna in ערלה Orlah that speaks
about things that are not בטל, batel, objects, sort of types of
different types of fruit, ערלה Orlah's fruit of forbidden fruit first three
years, get mixed up, not בטל. batel. And the text says, and
the משנה Mishna there says, if it is the way to count
it, then it's not בטל, batel, meaning some types of items are
sold by number, some are sold by weight. Okay, so if you
ever go, you know, like if you went ראש השנה Rosh Hashana
right to buy a pomegranate or whatever, I think they sell pomegranates
by number, not by weight. Okay. Other types of things, it really
doesn't matter, it's not the significance of an apple is a significant
thing, it's how much apple. So it's about a question about weight.
So things that are sold by weight or by bag or by
bushel, those are not considered to have real significance in the independent
object. Things that are sold by number, that gives them real significance.
Now you can imagine that that's true in some cases, like you
know, like a what do you call it, like a car. But
there are other things that are sold, I remember when we discussed
this at my שיעור, shiur, that people came up with cases that
were counted by number that are completely insignificant as independent objects, but
for some reason they were sold by number. I'm trying to remember
what the case is. But anyway, that's a way the גמרא Gemara
uses to determine if the thing by itself has significance. If it's
just like an amount of stuff that happens to come in a
convenient package as one whole apple, but it's not significant qua apple,
then it can lose its identity. But if it's significant as the
object itself, you would sell it by number, then it does not
lose its identity. But there's a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan
and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish how to read that line in the
משנה. Mishna. Do you read it את שדרכו למנות, et shedarko limnot,
things that are sold only by number or at least primarily by
number? Or do you read the line in the משנה, Mishna, כל
שדרכו למנות, kol shedarko limnot, anything that is could be sold by
number, is sometimes sold by number? There's a big difference by things
that are only or primarily sold by number as opposed to things
that are at times sold by number. Okay, so that is the
debate. So if you talk about a חתיכה chaticha of meat, the
גמרא Gemara assumes that you don't only sell that by number. If
anything, primarily you sell meat by the pound. But you could imagine
a place that sells individual, you know, chops of like a rib
steak or whatever, but that's also because they basically know roughly how
much it weighs.
But okay, anyway, whatever, you could imagine.
So that is not a case that is primarily sold by number.
It could occasionally be sold by number. So can we use the
idea of sold by number as a way of saying it's not
בטל? batel? It depends if your standard is primarily sold by number
or is your standard sometimes sold by number. So let's read that.
ותבטל ברוב, v'tibatel berov, let this חתיכה chaticha of meat become בטל
ברוב. batel berov. הניחא למאן דאמר, hani'cha l'man d'amar, it makes sense
according to the one that says כל שדרכו למנות שנינו. kol shedarko
limnot shaninu. The text in the משנה Mishna is anything whose way
it is to sell by number, למנות, limnot, to you know, to
count. So then it has significance and it won't be בטל. batel.
אלא למאן דאמר את שדרכו למנות שנינו, ela l'man d'amar et shedarko
limnot shaninu,
if you say, if you say you know, that which is, you
know, that which is sold by number, meaning it's much more specific,
it is only or at least primarily sold by number, מאי איכא
למימר, mai ika l'meimar, then that's not an answer, that's not true
by meat. So the גמרא Gemara is going to introduce that whole
discussion in a minute, but that's what it's about. So you can't
say that it's because it's sold by number, at least according to
one opinion, that's not primarily the case. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, here's another reason why a חתיכה chaticha of meat is important.
שאני חתיכה, shani chaticha,
a cut of meat is important, הואיל וראויה להתכבד בה לפני האורחים,
ho'il v're'uyah l'hitkabed bah lifnei ha'orchim,
because you use it as a way to honor guests. Okay, so
a nice slice of meat, right, a nice cut of a, you
know, of a rib steak, is something you would put in front
of an honored guest. So even if it's sold by weight, the
fact that this has significance as like a rib steak, that is
something that is given, it gives it weight and, no pun, and
significance and prevents it from becoming בטל. batel. So now we have
three categories. The גמרא Gemara basically said, rejected the assumption in our
משנה Mishna that independent objects are never בטל, batel, and said no
no no, the general rule is they are, the reason they're not
in our משנה Mishna are special cases. What are the special cases
in the משנה? Mishna? בריה, berya, a whole item like a גיד
הנשה, gid hanasheh, which is defined as an independent object as we
said before because the תורה Torah explicitly prohibits a גיד הנשה. gid
hanasheh. Other ideas are maybe because it was once part of a
living thing and so on, so we discussed last time what some
of the parameters of בריה berya are. Or something that is sold
primarily by number. Or the third category are things that you place
in front of, like as an honored piece, you know, a piece
of, sort of that is a way of respecting somebody that you
give. present this type of a thing in front of somebody. There
is an interesting sort of discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim or subtle
difference, but first of all a major discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim
about what type of חתיכה chaticha is considered ראויה להתכבד rauya lehitchabed
and how much processing does it have to be? Meaning, let’s say
you have a huge side of beef, okay? So you don’t put
a side of beef in front of somebody, but but is that
so therefore it's not of that category? Or because since it can
be cut up, it and you know it is of that category.
Let's say you have a chicken that is yet to be plucked.
Obviously, you would not put that in front of somebody, but is
the fact that it's lacking processing, you know,
should that factor in or not? That's a major debate. There’s also
a debate about you know some say the bigger, the more important,
just because you know processing doesn’t isn’t isn’t something that gets in
the way. If it's very small or maybe it's made into chopped
meat, that's a different story. But if you could get to that
nice slice, and others say no, right now it doesn't have that
significance. The other issue is some ראשונים Rishonim will talk about this
as a category as or שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch it's most famous
חתיכה הראויה להתכבד, chaticha harauya lehitchabed, a type of slice that is
normally as a way fit for honoring people with. The really what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is a standard חתיכה chaticha is assumed
to be ראויה להתכבד rauya lehitchabed and that's the way the רמב"ם
Rambam says it. So you don’t if you have at least by
cut of meat, not a cut of other things. So if you
have a cut of meat, you know, would you say, oh well,
yeah, but it's a it's a like it's an inexpensive cut, it's
not a fancy cut, it's not a rib steak, you know, would
you assume is your assumption that a cut of meat is ראויה
להתכבד? rauya lehitchabed? So there's a subtle difference between if you say
חתיכה chaticha is ראויה להתכבד rauya lehitchabed or חתיכה הראויה להתכבד, chaticha
harauya lehitchabed, which means that not all slices are that way, only
certain slices are that way. But anyway, there's a debate in the
ראשונים Rishonim how to determine the parameters, but the basic assumption is
that even יבש ביבש, yavesh beyavesh, independent items where you can certainly
hear the logic why ביטול bitul shouldn't work. Each item is independent.
If I pick up one item and put them in my mouth,
maybe I'm putting the טריפה treife in my mouth. If it's all
been blended together, I can say, yes, there's טריפה treife here, but
it's lost its identity. But if I put this piece in my
mouth, maybe I'm putting טריפה treife in my mouth and that’s all
I’m putting in my mouth. And nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara assumes that
even though it’s יבש ביבש, yavesh beyavesh, the presence of not knowing
which is which and the presence of other objects of a majority
of other objects cause ביטול bitul and the only question is and
the only point is there are some exceptions: בריה, birya, things that
are counted, things that are fit for honoring people with, guests with,
and so on. One last point and then I’ll take the question.
The גמרא Gemara here says רוב, rov, even a simple majority would
be enough. And the ראשונים Rishonim say yes, actually that's true if
it is all מין במינו, min bemino, like and like, because then
even if you were to cook it together, you wouldn't get the
taste of the other thing. So imagine this, you have chopped meat
here, not ראויה להתכבד, rauya lehitchabed, right? A pound of chopped meat,
and not sold by count by number, pound of chopped meat, three
separate packages of pounds of chopped meat, hamburger meat. Two are כשר,
kosher, one is נבילה, nevela, okay? And they got mixed up together.
You are allowed to eat all of them. You’re allowed to mix
them all up, make. Now some ראשונים Rishonim say maybe you should
eat them separately because if you eat them all together, you’re clearly
eating איסור, issur, but at least you could certainly make hamburgers out
of them, have three separate meals, עס געזונטהייט. es gezuntahait. The only
time where you really go by רוב rov if you don't have
one of these exceptions. If, however, it was they were like and
unlike, so then we don't let you eat them, then we would
need שישים, shishim, not stated explicitly in the גמרא, Gemara, but then
you’d need שישים shishim because then there would be a concern that
you would have cooked you would cook them all together and the
taste would disperse, so therefore you need sixty in order to ensure
that even were you to accidentally mix it up with the other
taste, you would still have enough to negate the taste. But that
becomes now the classic thing that you sort of I put in
front of my students, you know, at the very beginning is this
chart, to imagine a chart where this side says יבש ביבש, yavesh
beyavesh, לח בלח, lach belach, and this side says מין במינו min
bemino and מין באינו מינו. min be'eino mino. And the basic I
could show it to you, but I try to try to follow
visually here. So in this upper left hand corner, what's my upper
left, in this upper corner here, יבש ביבש yavesh beyavesh מין במינו,
min bemino, that's our case. It’s all dry, it’s not cooked together,
so there’s no taste, and it’s it’s all like and like, so
there’s not even a potential possibility of taste. רוב rov is enough.
Three separate packages of hamburger meat, רוב rov is enough biblically and
rabbinically. You can ממש mamash go ahead and eat it. That's what
our גמרא Gemara says when you don't have an exception. Down there
in this opposite corner, לח בלח lach belach מין באינו מינו, min
be'eino mino, apples and oranges, liquid and liquid, meaning it's a homogeneous
mass and it's liquid and liquid. There, the taste disperses throughout and
it’s a different taste. That's where there's a problem of the biblical
problem of טעם, ta'am, טעם כעיקר, ta'am k'ikar, right? If you get
a piece of חזיר chazer that gets mixed up and become, you
know, in your stew, and you know or חזיר chazer fat in
your stew, it all disperses, so you have taste is a real
issue. There you need שישים shishim or there is טעם ta'am and
that’s biblical. The other two quadrants because they’re somewhat similar to the
sixty requirement. Right in the case of לח בלח lach b'lach but
it's like and like, apples and apples, that's what we've been discussing
for the last few דפים, dapim, it all gets cooked together, but
there's really no taste. But because theoretically there could be taste if
it was apples and oranges, you still need sixty. That's the whole
previous דף daf that even if it's meat and meat being cooked
together, you need sixty, right? You remember those cases. And then what
I'm telling you right now is this quadrant as well, like and
unlike, but if it's separate items, you also need sixty because it's
connected to this, it's similar to the most problematic case, but that's
rabbinic. So biblically, the only case you need sixty or taste is
לח בלח מין בשאינו מינו. lach b'lach min b'sheino mino. Completely mixed
together and different tastes, because there you could taste it. Any other
taste, if it's not mixed together or it's like and like, apples
and apples, since there's no taste issue, the taste doesn't disperse or
it's all the same taste, you really only need majority. Rabbinically, you
need sixty in those cases as well, but the one case that's
salvaged is our case right here. They're not mixed together and they
have the same taste, so it's the furthest away from the case
of dispersed with taste and problematic taste. So in that case, this
upper left-hand or upper whatever corner here, that is a case where
you have separate packages of chopped meat, not mixed together, all the
same, you can go ahead and eat them. Okay. Now, question, starting
with Michael.
Well, first of all, I mean it says חתיכה של דג שנתבשלה
עם חתיכות, chaticha shel dag she'nitbashla im chatichot, so they don't mix
together the juices exude from there?
Oh, so that is a good question. Why there? No, because that's
true, once you do cook them together you need שישים, shishim, and
the משנה mishna says you need שישים. shishim. It says in
our משנה mishna says first of all, and if you can be
מכיר בנותן טעם. makir b'noten taam. So our משנה mishna says you
have to make sure there's no taste, and then it says and
you have to get rid of the item itself. If you, but
if you can't identify the offending item, then it's all forbidden. So
we have to say why isn't it בטל. batel. So we have
to give all of these reasons about it's important, it's a בריה,
biryah, it's חתיכה הראויה להתכבד, chaticha hare'uyah lehitchabed, etc. Okay, when but
it says what I'm talking about now is not the משנה mishna
case, when the גמרא gemara says let it be בטל ברוב, batel
b'rov, that indicates that if you were not to be cooking it
together, and you didn't have the dispersal of taste and the only
problem you had is the problem we're being presented with, separate objects
mixed together, but independent objects, there רוב rov should be enough. That
is certainly what almost all the ראשונים rishonim assume. There are some
that disagree. There are some that say even this upper quadrant, even
that chopped meat, those different packages of chopped meat still require, still
require sixty rabbinically, but that's not how we rule.
I was trying to figure out how we fit this into the
case where you have nine pieces of meat from a kosher place
and one from a...
Total, I wouldn't say total different, some want to say that that's
the way it works, that if I pick up this one package
of the chopped meat and there are two others, I say well,
maybe it's the other
two, the most likely scenario is that this one package I'm picking
up is the kosher one, two to one, so I can eat
it. Then I pick up the second package and I say the
same thing. This is probably the kosher one, each it's two to
one. Then I pick up the third package and I say this
is probably the kosher one, and by the end of the day
I've eaten all three, with each package I was allowed to assume
it was from the majority set. That is how some of the
ראשונים rishonim explain ביטול, bitul, but I should say that that's not
the פשט. pshat. The פשט pshat is that here the concept is
when it's a mixture, the presence of a majority of other items
makes this item considered to lose its identity, even though the only
reason they're mixed is because I can't identify as opposed to a
physical mixture. Okay, but what you are saying is the way some
ראשונים rishonim understand it. Let me just go to Charlie. Yeah, Charlie.
Just, you're talking about this in the context of כשרות, kashrut, does
this extend to ערלה orlah or טבל tevel or mixtures of?
Yes, there actually the משניות mishnayot are more explicit about the problem
about
that ביטול, bitul, about בצלי דומא bitzlei duma and so on. But
there when it says that it does work, it says it works
in things like one in a hundred and those types of cases,
remember those were some of the scenarios over there. It's never explicit
whether by ערלה orlah or by
what do you call it, טבל, tevel, or by normal כשרות kashrut
issues, that רוב rov is enough to be a
ביטול bitul by separate objects. There if you remember מין במינו min
b'mino was greater stringency. So there if it's אינו מינו eino mino
you're going to need sixty and if it's מינו mino you're going
to need a hundred or two hundred. It's only here where מינו
mino is a leniency that we actually say majority is enough and
it's mind-blowing. Like I said, three separate... Again, if you mixed all
the hamburger meat together, that would be לח בלח, lach b'lach, that
would be sixty. But as separate packages, you could really
eat all... a simple majority, you just... well, here you just need
two to one. But there's even a discussion of, just to really
blow your mind, let's say you had 51 packages of kosher chopped
meat and 49 of non-kosher. You had a one percent majority. In
theory, you could eat everything. But there though, there the ראשונים rishonim
take pause and they say we do want, there are those that
say no, no, we're going to want... But not necessarily. There are
those that say even a simple majority would be enough. Last question,
then we're going to move on.
This maybe a part of the justification when they had the Monsey
chicken scandal.
Rabbi Tendler told people they didn't have to kasher their pots because
the guy was also selling a lot of כשר kosher chicken.
Right. So that is yeah so okay I won't get into that
but yeah but that's also בטל batel you know and again taste
is not you're not eating טרפה treifa itself you know that questions
about טעם כעיקר taam ke-ikkar and especially if you wait a day
then all then it's all דרבנן derabbanan any absorbed taste. So
but yeah okay very last question from Simon.
I don't see conceptually
why would you say it should be conceptually be any different than
like those nine pieces of meat from those nine stores? I don't
see conceptually why would you say it should be conceptually be any
different than like those nine pieces of meat from those nine stores?
It might but it could why would it be better? It's certainly
as good as that. The question is is that it might be
better. The question is in the case of if I want to
treat it like the nine stores I have to eat
each item separately
right because I have to be able to say in each one
maybe this is the כשר kosher and also at the end of
the day I have to be able to accept the fact that
I definitely ate טרפה. treifa. As opposed to if you want to
say ביטול bitul you can in theory eat them together and you
don't have to say you ate טרפה treifa because you could say
הלכה halacha says that it's lost its identity. Why what makes it
better is that it's a group, it's a mixture. And the fact
that even though the mixture is created by my ignorance, but the
fact that it's a mixture means that I can say that what
I have present here is the majority of the other objects overwhelm
the minority object. Okay? It's like it's sort of you know the
whole thing about being lost in the crowd. Remember those pictures which
is has like a whole an ice floe full of no no
of penguins right? Totally look the same and one guy is you
know dancing and saying I've just got to be me. So
you know so here it's like if you're lost in the crowd
what do you mean to retain your identity. So if you're a
בריה beryah or if you're you know if you're חתיכה הראויה להתכבד
hatikhah hare'uyah lehitkabbed or דרכו למנות darko limnot you're a dancing penguin
okay you can retain your identity but otherwise you all become part
of a homogeneous mass even though they are separate items. That's the
assumption here. Okay you had one last question last last question.
If the woman knows this is
non-כשר kosher and she mixes it with no not intentionally.
This is it it got the mixture happened accidentally. You are not
allowed to intentionally create a mixture אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה. ein mevatlin
issur lekhathillah. We're going to see about that.
But she knows
that there is non-כשר.
kosher. Sure.
But I don't understand let's say let's say you dropped accidentally a
little bit of let's say somebody pours here's an example somebody takes
some tomato sauce pours it into their stew and sauce or whatever
and then oh all of a sudden looks at the can and
says oh my god it doesn't have a הכשר hekhsher and it
says it says it has
meat as one of the ingredients right? So obviously you got some
טרפה treifa meat going on now. So calls up the rabbi. So
is rabbi going to say oh there's טרפה treifa meat you absolutely
cannot eat it or he might say well how much meat was
it proportional to how much stew? And if it was only טרפה
treifa amount or whatever then בדיעבד bedieved it's okay. Although most housewives
would throw it out anyway and maybe that's what you're saying. But
the point is is that but you're eating טרפה treifa as a
little bit of meat here. But that's the principle of ביטול. bitul.
If you have an overwhelming proportion and here what's shocking is even
a majority but if then it's considered like it nullifies the forbidden
thing, it loses its identity and you're no longer eating טרפה. treifa.
That's the חידוש hiddush of this. But that's every time somebody calls
the rabbi as I accidentally mixed something with something else right? That's
a case where in the end if the rabbi says it's okay
he's going to let you eat something that's not כשר kosher but
it stops being not כשר kosher because the הלכה halacha says that
this negates its identity and makes it permissible.
Yes Sarah.
Say someone purchased baked beans and didn't realize they were
pork and beans
not that
okay anyway yes
and they're making this you're making this whole meal and the meat
and everything else on the plate that you serve is totally כשר
kosher and you put baked beans on the same plate. Now you
haven't mixed the baked beans with meat but it's on the plate
with כשר kosher things. Is that everything is not כשר kosher
now right?
The plate everything.
No, it doesn't to in order for non-כשר kosher to transfer it
has to be there has to be heat and touching together and
heat transfers from one object to another. So if they're just sitting
next to each other it doesn't transfer. Now does it go into
the plate and from the plate into the thing? But depending on
how hot everything is maybe theoretically. But basically no. You need to
be through heat taste transfers otherwise no. Okay let's move on. Okay
so now the גמרא Gemara says
וצריכא. u-tzrikhah. Okay back to the גמרא. Gemara. We need both cases
of the גיד gid and of the and of the nice cut
of meat to tell you that both of those are exceptions.
If you just tell me the גיד gid because it's a בריה,
birya, that has significance because it's an entire item and it's an
item of a חתיכה, chaticha, but just a chop of meat, even
a nice cut of meat, אימא לא, eima lo, it's not the
category of בריה, birya, which is a very distinct category that you
get lashes even if it's not a כזית k'zayis and so on.
ואי אשמעינן חתיכה, Ve-i ashmi'unan chaticha, if it said the slice of
meat, that is maybe subjectively important טוב ראוי להתכבד בו לפני אורחים
tov re-uy le-hitkabed bo lifnei orchim because you would give it to
a way of honoring guests. אבל גיד, Aval gid, but even though
a גיד gid is halachically a בריה, birya, it's not something that
societally we really care about, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe that's not
important. צריכא, Tzericha, which basically means one has if you would sort
of objective or legal significance, a גיד gid has legal significance because
it's an entire item, but it doesn't do anything for me, what
do I care if it's a גיד gid or the whole גיד
gid or not. And this other something else has societal significance, subjective
significance, the slice of meat, although not other ways of having legal
significance and either one is enough to give it to have it
retain its identity and not be nullified and be an exception to
the nullification. Now we are moving on. דרש רבה בר בר חנה,
Darash Raba bar bar Chana, as if that was not enough of
a big idea, חתיכה של נבילה של דג טמא, chaticha shel neveilah
shel dag tamei, going on the case of the משנה, Mishnah, you
have a chunk of meat a cut of meat or a piece
of non-kosher fish, ואינה אוסרת, ve-eina oseret, would not make the rest
of the pot forbidden, עד שתתן טעם ברוטב ובקיפה ובחתיכות, ad she-titein
taam berotev u-ve-kippa u-ve-chatichot,
until it spread now you cooked it with other stuff with potatoes
and carrots and whatever you cooked it with, it only forbids the
stew if it gave taste through into all of the items, which
means another way of saying what we said earlier that when you
need sixty of opposite or when you measure the things that have
dispersed the taste, you measure everything in the pot, the sauce, the
potatoes, the gook at the bottom, and therefore you have to say
is there that much quantity all this stuff was there enough of
the forbidden thing to give taste into all of this other stuff?
So that's how they basically not a really new idea from what
we said before. But קיפה kippa is like the gook at the
bottom. Technically speaking, it's a very technical term. Now אוקי רבא אמורא
עליה, u-ki Rava mora alei, now רב Rav however wanted to make
a qualification to that statement and to say that there's ways in
which that actually that we have to be more strict in that
case, in a special case. What's the case? So he had an
אמורא, amora, he placed an אמורא amora on him, which means an
אמורא Amora with a capital A is the people like רב Rav
and רבא Rava and אביי Abaye and all the people we see
all the rabbis of the גמרא, Gemara, the same way a תנא
Tanna with capital T is like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But אמורא amora with
a lowercase a, I mean this figuratively, is the loudspeaker of the
אמורא, Amora, meaning he would say the אמורא amora would say something
to this person and then this person would yell it out to
the crowd. The same way the תנא tanna lowercase t is also
the person that would memorize all the material of the תנאים tannaim
and go and report it to other people, that's what Soloveitchik called
living books, their job was to memorize everything because it was in
an oral culture. So that was their job. Anyway, רב Rav had
an אמורא amora stand over him to proclaim the following qualification on
this statement. ודרש, Ve-darash, and he made the following exposition. כיון שנתן
טעם בחתיכה חתיכה עצמה נעשית נבילה ואוסרת כל החתיכות כולן מפני שהן
מינה. Keivan she-natan taam be-chaticha, chaticha atzma na'aseit neveilah, ve-oseret kol ha-chatichot
kulam mipnei she-hen mina. Now if you had the following special case
where you had your chunk of non-kosher meat and it didn't fall
straight into the stew. First it was cooked separately, sometimes how you
braise brown the meat before you put it into the טשולנט cholent
or whatever. So anyway you cooked it separately with one let's say
even one piece of meat and then you dumped it in the
stew. So there's two stages. Non-kosher is first cooked with one piece
of kosher meat and then both are put into the stew. So
כיון שנתן טעם בחתיכה, keivan she-natan taam be-chaticha, it gave taste to
one חתיכה chaticha before it was put into the entire stew, it
first had a יחידות yechidut with one of the חתיכות, chatichot, and
then they were both put in the stew. What it did then,
חתיכה עצמה נעשית נבילה. chaticha atzma na'aseit neveilah. This is another big
concept in כשרות, kashrus, often abbreviated as חענ"ן, Chet Ayin Nun Nun,
חתיכה עצמה נעשית נבילה, chaticha atzma na'aseit neveilah, or sometimes just חנ"ן,
Chet Nun Nun, חתיכה נעשית נבילה, chaticha na'aseit neveilah, and therefore I
meant עין, ayin, excuse me. You mean אלף? alef? No, חתיכה עצמה,
chaticha atzmah, oh עצמה, atzmah, this is a חת. chat. No, no,
חתיכה עצמה. chaticha atzmah. Anyway so sometimes when you're learning they're always
talking about חנ"ן, Chanan, חנ"ן, Chanan, so somebody walks in and says
who's this חנ"ן Chanan character? It's like you see people talk about
טעם כעיקר, taam ke-ikkar, טעם כעיקר, taam ke-ikkar, taste is like the
thing itself. So if you're in בית מדרש beis medrash they talk
about טעם כעיקר, taam ke-ikkar, טעם כעיקר. taam ke-ikkar. So what's the
taste of this cookie, of this piece of this bread of this
roll or whatever. Anyway, right. So anyway this principle is that if
it gave taste to this חתיכה, chaticha, we don't just say this
חתיכה chaticha now becomes a carrier of the taste of נבילה. neveilah.
Since it became forbidden, it's like the entire identity of the חתיכה
chaticha now becomes a נבילה neveilah itself. You have a new one.
Let's go into it. You have number one which is the נבלה
neveilah, *neveila*. It's cooked with or let's call it A. A is
the נבלה neveilah, *neveila*. It's cooked with piece number one. So one
does not just become a carrier for the taste of A, for
the taste of the נבלה *neveila*, it itself becomes another A. Its
whole identity now, or call it an N. Its whole identity now,
right, both of them are N, become נבלה *neveila*. And therefore, if
they're now both put in the pot, you don't just need 60
opposite opposite N number 1, you need 60 opposite N1 plus N2.
Okay, and that is the idea that once something becomes אסור assur.
*assur* because of taste, we don't just treat it as a carrier
for the taste and that it has some minute traces, but because
it becomes forbidden, it's like its whole identity becomes now the forbidden
thing and now you need to be מבטל mevatel, *mevatel* both pieces.
Let's just read it and then I'll take your question. כיון שנתן
טעם בחתיכה keivan she-natan ta'am be-chatichah, *keivan she-natan ta'am b'chaticha*, since it
gives taste, N gave taste into number item number one, חתיכה chatichah.
עצמה נעשית נבלה *chaticha atzmah na'aseis neveila*, item number one switches and
becomes from a one to an N, ואוסרת כל החתיכות כולן *ve-oseret
kol ha-chatichot kulan*. And now what it should have said is it
makes all of the items forbidden because you don't have 60 opposite
the two together. The problem the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to have
is it says it makes all of the items forbidden מפני שהיא
מינה *mipnei she-hi minah* because you have other chunks of meat there,
and assuming this is assuming like רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* that מין
במינו לא בטל batel *min b'mino lo batel*. So the other chunks
of meat cannot negate other chunks of meat. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s obvious question is then who cares that one became an N?
Even if you just have the N itself, the other chunks can't
be מבטל mevatel *mevatel* if it's רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*. So let's
read the answer. Charlie, don't forget your question, I'll get back to
you, but let's not lose our train of thought. So אמר ליה
רב ספרא לאביי *amar lei Rav Safra l'Abaye*, Rav Safra said to
Abaye, מכדי *michdi* let's take a look. רב כמאן אמרה לשמעתיה *Rav
k'man amrah l'shmateih*, who is Rav speaking according to? כרב יהודה *k'Rav
Yehuda*, he was assuming the position of Rav Yehuda דאמר מין במינו
לא בטל batel *d'amar min b'mino lo batel*, like and like is
not בטל batel *batel* because he said all the other chunks are
forbidden because they're the same, they're all the same, they're they're all
meat. So that's an assumption of Rav Yehuda that like and like
is never בטל batel *batel*. So if that's true, מאי איריא כי
נתן טעם ta'am, *mai irya ki natan ta'am*, who cares that N
first had יחידות *yechidus* there with number one and gave taste into
it? אפילו לא נתן נמי *afilu lo natan nami*, even forgetting that
whole thing, if there's one chunk of treif meat and 100 chunks
of kosher meat and you assume like Rav Yehuda, who needs to
turn it into two chunks of treif meat? That thing is not
בטל batel *batel* because like and like is not בטל batel, *batel*
according to Rav Yehuda. So אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he says,
הכא במאי עסקינן בשקדם וסילקו *hacha b'mai askinan b'she-kadam v'silko*. No, no,
no, the case is you removed the non-kosher, the original N. Okay,
so here's what happened, you cooked N with number one and then
you threw out the נבלה *neveila*. And then you put number one,
which is now N-prime, okay, the second N, right, into the pot.
So if it were just the case of of Rav Yehuda's מין
במינו *min b'mino*, then it was like, okay, no problem, all I
have here is I have maybe the taste of N but I
don't have N itself, I don't have forbidden meat itself, so maybe
I can do ביטול bitul. *bitul*. But because we're saying that one
becomes not just a carrier for taste, but becomes N-prime, it becomes
a treif piece of meat itself, then we have מין במינו לא
בטל batel *min b'mino lo batel*, then it's not negated by the
other things. So the point is you're right, if you had the
original N, well according to Rav Yehuda ever, if you had the
original N in the pot, you wouldn't need this special case, מין
במינו לא בטל batel, *min b'mino lo batel* according to Rav Yehuda.
But we're talking that you don't have the original N in the
pot, and if one was just treated as a carrier, then although
there's taste, we would have said maybe the taste is negated. But
because number one becomes N-prime, is treated like treif meat, and there's
other meat here, מין במינו לא בטל batel. *min b'mino lo batel*
and you can't have ביטול bitul, *bitul*. But the more relevant application
of this ruling is we don't since we don't rule like Rav
Yehuda is that when you have N and N-prime both there, you
need you need not 60 times one unit but 60 times two
units, that it's not just seen as you basically have just one
unit of forbidden stuff with some of its taste circulating around. Once
it gave its taste into one piece separately, then it becomes two
units of forbidden stuff. Yeah, well that is well, not everyone, that's
what comes out of this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. The reason you have
these huge תוספות *Tosafot* is because there's a position of רבנו אפרים
*Rabbeinu Ephraim* and a very cogent position and other ראשונים *Rishonim* or
whatever, that more or less say we don't rule like this גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara*, that while that basically say we might rule like that
when it comes to cooking meat and milk together, there's another גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* there and there it makes sense, but here basically they
have a way of bracketing this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and saying we
don't really rule like it. So we actually, so it's basically so
we actually rule like it, we basically basically מחלוקת ספרדים Sefardim ואשכנזים
*machlokes Sefardim v'Ashkenazim*. ספרדים Sefardim *Sefardim* once again are more lenient and
they don't rule like this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and the and therefore
they would say if you have N giving taste into one and
it's not בשר בחלב *basar b'chalav*, then you only need 60 times
one unit and אשכנזים Ashkenazim, *Ashkenazim* basically rule like this גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* and say that no, if it first gave taste into one
and then both pieces were put in the pot, if it goes
in the pot straight, then you you need 60 times one, but
if it's separate and then they both go in the pot, then
you need then you need 120 not 60. Okay, let's see where.
60 times two is 120. 120. Okay, and that's, so that's the
basic אשכנזים Ashkenazim, פסקן, pasken, which by the way, going back to
my scenario of the, of the tomato sauce that's meat, right? When
you taste that tomato sauce and then you pour it into the
soup, do you need 60 times the tomato sauce or just 60
times the trace amount of meat in the tomato sauce? That's this
question. Now, you might not, even according to אשכנזים, Ashkenazim you might
not say חנאן Chanan here because tomato sauce is not a חתיכה.
It's a liquid, okay? And therefore, there are some opinions that it
doesn't, it only applies when something is like a unit, we say
the whole unit becomes נבלה, but if it's just liquid, you know,
we might not say. That is a highly relevant question anytime a
rabbi gets a שאלה, shailah, if it's not, not if it's meat
and milk, this only applies by non-kosher. Meat and milk, you totally
go by the proportion of the offending, of the offending ingredient. But
by non-kosher, because of this גמרא Gemara and according to אשכנזים, Ashkenazim
it might not just be based about, about the trace amounts of
the original. If it first went into a product, product, and from
there into whatever you're doing, that whole thing might have to be
treated like the forbidden object, based on this גמרא Gemara according to
אשכנזים Ashkenazim and based on parameters that are worked out in the.
It's already בטל batel in the can? No, no, no. It's already
בטל batel. in the can, then the אשכנזים Ashkenazim agree as well.
The question is it's not בטל batel. in the tomato sauce, but
it's certainly בטל once the tomato sauce gets in your soup. So
the ספרדים only want to know about the original trace amounts. The
אשכנזים say if it wasn't בטל in the can, maybe the whole
thing is אסור. assur. Yeah, of course. For instance, the pork and
beans situation. There you'd have identifiable beans and the meat is trace
amounts. Right, exactly that case. If it's less than 60 though, then
it's okay. But if it wasn't בטל, כיון שנתן טעם ta'am, בחתיכה,
if it gave taste, which presumably it does there, right, then the
whole thing might become אסור. assur But then there's a question if
it's a liquid as opposed to a solid and so on. So
my real question was you said it becomes נבלה, does that apply
to other things like טומאה? tumah? טומאה, Tumah, no. It applies to
other forbidden, only for כשרות. kashrut. And even for כשרות kashrut it's
heavily debated. Let's just read through the משנה Mishnah and then I'll
take your question. We are almost as you can see, this is
like one of the most dense and intense motherlode here, primary כשרות
kashrut ideas. אפילו תימא לא קדם וסילקו. Afilu teima lo kadam ve-silko.
And now the גמרא Gemara says or was there an אמורא Amora
stated there? רבא אמר, Rava amar, thank you. רבא אמר אפילו תימא
לא קדם וסילקו. Rava amar afilu teima lo kadam ve-silko. Here's another
way in which it's relevant for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, not that
you removed the original N. You didn't, so why, so why isn't
it just בטל because of all the other pieces of meat? Because
it's מין במין min be-min according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Nevertheless,
הוי מינו ודבר אחר. haviah mino ve-davar acher. It's, it's like and
like and unlike. What's the unlike? There's a lot of meat here,
but there's potatoes and carrots and water and so on. וכל מינו
ודבר אחר, Ve-chol mino ve-davar acher, even according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, when you have like and like and unlike, meaning, the like
meaning apple, forbidden meat, other pieces of meat, kosher meat, and then
potatoes and carrots and so on, סלקינן מינו כמי שאינו, salkinan mino
k-mi she-eino, ignore the kosher pieces of meat. ושאינו מינו רבה עליו
ומבטלו, U-she-eino mino rabbah alav u-mevatlo, he will allow the meat, the
carrots and the potatoes and the liquid to negate it. So according
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says like and like is not
בטל, okay? He doesn't say that the presence of other pieces of
meat prevents ביטול. bitul He just says the presence of other pieces
of meat, when they're non-kosher piece of meat, won't effect ביטול, bitul.
but it's like they're irrelevant, the other pieces of meat. So let's
say I have one tref piece of meat, a couple of pieces
of kosher meat, and I put in a pot with tons of
potatoes and water and other stuff. So then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
would say, okay, it's בטל. You ignore the kosher meat, it's irrelevant,
and the presence of the potatoes and the carrots, the אינו מינו,
eino mino, if it's 60, you know, if it's big enough, let's
say 60 times as much, that negates the non-kosher piece of meat.
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda could allow for ביטול in that scenario.
And that's why even according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda it matters
that number one became N prime. Why? Because that's your case. If
you had N falling into the pot, there were let's say 10
units of kosher meat, and you know, 50 units of potatoes and
liquid or whatever, so there would have been, not a 60 units
of potato and liquid or whatever. So you ignore the kosher meat,
60 units against your N, it would have created ביטול. Because N
turned number one into N prime and they're both in the pot,
now you have to be מבטל, mevatel? you need 120 of the
potatoes and the water and so on, and you don't have it.
If N just primed the stone, then what? Then you need 60.
Okay, so once again we see though the principle of רבא Rava
is once it makes one item forbidden, now you need to negate
quantitatively 60 times as much as that entire item, not just the
tref amounts that it contains. But there's a major question if we
rule like this גמרא. Gemara אשכנזים say yes, ספרדים say no, leads
to big issues like I say, when you buy a product that's
not בטל and then you mix it up, you might have to
go by the whole product, not just by the original tref amount.
Quick, very quick question before we go, we're going to finish the
דף daf today. About the חתיכה נעשית נבלה, chatichah na'aseit neveilah, so
you're saying, so the meat you wouldn't necessarily. serve the potatoes, right?
That would not be חתיכה הראויה. chaticha hareuyah. Right, but the meat
you would, you can fish it out, so does that change anything
in other words or not? Because otherwise—Yeah, if there are pieces of
meat that are fit to serve לפני אורחים lifnei orchim depending on
how you define those criteria, then even if there are 60 times
as much and even if you can't identify the טרייף treif piece
of meat, you can't eat anything because that piece of meat will
never become בטל. That's exactly what we said. That's our—But we're still
having the potatoes מבטל the meat. You can eat the potatoes, you
can't eat the meat. Oh, you can't eat any of the meat?
Even though the meat is מבטל? Right, so just to give you
that scenario because that is the case in the משנה, mishna, so
you went ahead and you cooked, you know, you had my stew,
right, with these chunks of meat and assuming that a chunk even
from a stew chunk could you would give to an honored guest,
which is questionable, but let's for the sake of it assume that,
okay, because that's like the case in the משנה. mishna. So if
there's 60 times of 60 of the kosher products for meat and
the potatoes and all the kosher stuff, so you can eat the
potatoes because the potatoes don't have the taste of טרייף treif meat,
that's been dispersed. But you can't eat any of the chunks of
meat. Why? Because that's what we said. If it's ראויה להתכבד, reuyah
lihitchabed, it doesn't get בטל. Okay, and since you can't identify which
is the offending one, you can't eat any of the chunks of
meat, but you could eat the potatoes because those don't have taste
because that's been dispersed. So what's—There's בטול? bittul? There's בטול bittul in
the potatoes, the potatoes have negated the taste. But there's no בטול
bittul in these chunks of meat because ראויה להתכבד reuyah lihitchabed prevented
בטול. bittul. Okay, but if it wasn't ראויה להתכבד, reuyah lihitchabed, then
you could eat the chunks of meat. Let's move on. All right,
we've done a major work in terms of כשרות kashrus and now
we are going to get back to גיד הנשה. Gid Hanasheh. We'll
go back to כשרות kashrus next פרק. perek. Okay, נוהג בטהורה ואינו
נוהג בטמאה. Noheig bitehorah ve'eino noheig bitmeiah. The גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh
applies משנה mishna in kosher animals, not in non-kosher animals. For, we'll
see why in the גמרא, Gemara you know, the most logical reason
is because the תורה Torah is forbidding it from an animal that
otherwise you could eat. We're assuming you're eating the animal, but don't
eat the גיד. gid. Okay, the גמרא Gemara will give other reasons
why—מצות המלך. mitzvas hamelech. Right, so if you eat the גיד, gid,
if you eat the גיד gid of let's say I don't know,
a camel, then you get lashed. Now do you get lashed or
not? Well, this depends. So if the גיד gid does not have
taste, אין בגידין בנותן טעם, ein bigidin binosan taam, you don't get
lashed for eating camel meat because it's not considered camel meat, it
has no taste. Okay, so you don't transgress the prohibition of eating
camel and you don't transgress the prohibition of eating a גיד gid
because it only applies to kosher animals. So you wouldn't transgress anything.
It would be like eating the horn of a, the hoof of
a camel. If, however, we assume a גיד gid has taste, you
get lashes for eating camel, but you don't get lashes for eating
גיד gid because a גיד gid is not forbidden in non-kosher animals.
That's the opinion of the תנא קמא. tanna kamma. רבי יהודה אומר
אף בטמאה. Rabbi Yehuda omer af bitmeiah. It applies even by non-kosher
animals. אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda, and I'll tell you why.
והלא מבני יעקב נאסר גיד הנשה ועדיין בהמה טמאה מותרת להן. Vahalo
mibnei Yaakov ne'esar Gid Hanasheh ve'adayin behemah tmeiah muteres lahen. Because the
children of יעקב Yaakov couldn't eat the גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh and
they could eat camels. So if the תורה Torah says don't eat
a גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh and it's talking to the children of
יעקב's Yaakov's children, then it's basically saying don't eat the גיד הנשה
Gid Hanasheh even of camels, because it's all the same. The גמרא
Gemara frames it as בני נח, bnei Noach, but רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says specifically not בני נח, bnei Noach, not non-Jews, בני יעקב.
bnei Yaakov. מותרת להן. Mutteres lahen. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said
to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, בסיני נאמר. besinai ne'emar. No, no, no,
no, no. That פסוק pasuk על כן לא יאכלו בני ישראל, al
ken lo yochlu bnei Yisrael, right, it's an interesting question, what does
the word ישראל Yisrael mean in that פסוק? pasuk? בני ישראל, bnei
Yisrael, the sons of יעקב Yaakov called ישראל Yisrael or the children
of ישראל Yisrael with capital C capital I? So they say, no,
no, no, that פסוק pasuk על כן לא יאכלו al ken lo
yochlu was said, you know, whatever, 500 years later at הר סיני.
Har Sinai. However, when משה Moshe came to write the ספר תורה,
Sefer Torah, אלא שנכתב במקומו, ela shenichtav bimkomo, he figured might as
well write that because God told him, you know, don't write that
פסוק pasuk here in just a list of random, you know, of
many things like in קדושים תהיו Kedoshim Tihyu or משפטים. Mishpatim. No,
no, let's put that right in the in the actual narrative. But
that מצוה mitzvah was given at הר סיני Har Sinai and בני
ישראל bnei Yisrael means capital children of Israel, Israelites, and therefore it
is—you can't talk about, well, you know, what happened at the time
of יעקב. Yaakov. This is a very important רמב"ם Rambam I had
meant to bring in. I'll post it on the on my blog.
Where in his פירוש המשניות Peirush Hamishnayos where he says, remember this
principle, says the רמב"ם, Rambam, anything we observe today as Jews has
nothing to do with what was done prior to מתן תורה. Matan
Torah. The fact that we do ברית מילה bris milah is not
because אברהם Avraham did ברית מילה. bris milah.
And the fact that we do
גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh is not because יעקב Yaakov did it. And
the fact that we do anything is not because, although we say
the אבות avos instituted תפילה, tefillah, but he said we are doing
things because we were commanded as a people at הר סיני. Har
Sinai. So whatever happened prior, that's interesting as a history and that
was a precedent, but that's not what obligates us, right? We're not
obligated by, you know, because we're not obligated because why would we
be obligated just because we're, you know, you could say God said
to אברהם, Avraham, you and your descendants after you. But nevertheless for
it's very important for the רמב"ם Rambam that we are doing things
as, you know, because of הר סיני, Har Sinai, which also raises
an interesting question, which is, are we also included in בני נח?
bnei Noach? The שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva mitzvos bnei Noach, right,
that apply to בני נח, bnei Noach, do they apply to us?
I mean, we're also part of humanity or no, no, no. So
our מצוות mitzvot that are parallel those are based on הר סיני,
Har Sinai, not based on our identity as בני נח. Bnei Noach.
And the רמב"ם Rambam explicitly says that. He says the reason we
keep אבר מן החי eiver min hachai is not because בני נח
Bnei Noach were commanded in אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. That's
why they keep it. We keep it because we were commanded as
a people on הר סיני. Har Sinai. So it's an interesting also
sort of theological issue. I see a lot of questions. I'm going
to have to hold them off, I'm sorry. Let's read a little
of the גמרא. Gemara Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says like this:
וסבר רבי יהודה איסור חל על איסור. V'savar Rabbi Yehuda issur chal
al issur. Now you're always saying what, where did
that come from?
But the גמרא Gemara assumes that the problem in the משנה Mishnah
is not whether logically the תורה Torah refers to camels or not,
but a technical problem of how can you have one prohibition on
top of another. Assuming the גיד gid has taste and it's and
it's therefore prohibited as camel as well, so how can now something
that was already prohibited as camel get a new prohibition of גיד
הנשה? gid hanasheh? One can't take place on top of the other.
Now you'll say, don't they come at the same time? As soon
as the animal is born, it has both. So the גמרא Gemara
assumes that the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh prohibition comes only after the
animal is born and the animal is אסור assur as camel even
in its mother's womb. So therefore, how does the prohibition of גיד
הנשה gid hanasheh take place on top of the prohibition of camel?
So let's see what it says. והתניא, V'hatanya, didn't we teach in
a ברייתא, braita, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, יכול תהא נבלת
עוף טמא מטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה? Yachol tehei nevilat of tamei metamei
begadim b'veit habliya? We hold that if you eat a dead bird,
a dead כשר kosher bird that was not שחטed, shecht a נבילה
neveila of a כשר kosher bird and you swallow it, when you
swallow it, you become טמא, tamei, you and your clothes. So maybe,
says רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, this would apply even by dead non-כשר
kosher birds? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse teaches, נבילה וטרפה לא
יאכל לטמאה בה, neveila u'treifa lo yochel l'tamei vah, do not eat
a נבילה neveila or טריפה treifa to become טמא tamei thereby. So
this is the verse that tells you that eating a נבילה neveila
makes you טמא, tamei, and חז"ל Chazal understand that it's referring to
a נבילה neveila of a כשר kosher bird. Okay, so and it's
telling you that you become טמא. tamei. Now how does that tell
you it doesn't apply to a non-כשר kosher bird? So מי שאיסורו
משום בל תאכל נבילה. mi she'issuro mishum bal tochal neveila. We are
only prohibited or not prohibited, only having טומאה tumah by something which
is prohibited because of because it is a נבילה. neveila. יצא זה,
Yatza zeh, to exclude a dead non-כשר kosher bird, שאין איסורו משום
בל תאכל נבילה. she'ein issuro mishum bal tochal neveila. It's not prohibited
as a נבילה, neveila, אלא משום בל תאכל טמא. ela mishum bal
tochal tamei. So here he is saying, forget the טומאה tumah issue,
that's not relevant for us. He's saying a dead non-כשר kosher bird
is forbidden as a non-כשר kosher bird, it does not also become
a נבילה. neveila. Why doesn't it also become a נבילה? neveila? Just
because it died, it's dead, why isn't it a נבילה? neveila? So
the גמרא assumes because אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal
al issur. Once it's forbidden as a non-כשר kosher bird, it can't
also become forbidden as a נבילה. neveila. אלא משום בל תאכל טמא,
ela mishum bal tochal tamei, so therefore if he holds one איסור
issur cannot take place on another, how does he think that you
can have two prohibitions by the גיד הנשה? gid hanasheh? So we
have a good answer which we've been mentioning. וכי תימא קסבר אין
בגידין בנותן טעם. V'chi teima kasavar ein b'gidim b'noten ta'am. Maybe he
thinks the גיד gid has no טעם, ta'am, right, and that will
make it that they're not competing. If the גיד gid has no
טעם, ta'am. you eat the גיד gid of a camel, you have
not transgressed eating camel. Everybody with me? Right, because it has no
טעם, ta'am it's not forbidden as camel, but it could be forbidden
as a גיד. gid. ובטמא נמי איסור גיד איכא, U'vitamei nami issur
gid ika, and even by a camel, I'm using camel as an
example, right, it has the prohibition of the גיד, gid, איסור טומאה
ליכא, issur tumah leika, it's not prohibited as camel because it has
no טעם. ta'am, So that that would be a good answer. But
however, וסבר רבי יהודה אין בגידין בנותן טעם? V'savar Rabbi Yehuda ein
b'gidim b'noten ta'am? Can you really make that claim that he holds
there's no טעם to the גיד? gid? והתניא, V'hatanya, we taught in
the ברייתא, braita, האוכל גיד הנשה של בהמה טמאה, ha'ochel gid hanasheh
shel behema tmeia, if you eat a גיד הנשה gid hanasheh of
a camel, let's say, רבי יהודה מחייב שתים, Rabbi Yehuda mechayev shtayim,
he explicitly says you get two sets of lashes, one for camel
and one for גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. So you see he holds
it is forbidden as camel, it does have טעם, and he holds
it could have both prohibitions. How does he allow it to have
two prohibitions? רבי שמעון פוטר, Rabbi Shimon poter, and רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon exempts completely, and we'll discuss that tomorrow. So how do you
deal with it? So the גמרא says לעולם קסבר יש בגידין בנותן
טעם. Le'olam kasavar yesh b'gidim b'noten ta'am. Really yes, there are taste
and it's אסור assur in the גיד gid and it's אסור as
camel. How is it that they're not competing? וקסבר נוהג בשליא. V'kasavar
noheig b'shilya. He holds that the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh prohibition begins
even in utero, as a fetus. דאיסור גיד ואיסור טומאה בהדי הדדי
קא אתו. De'issur gid v'issur tumah bahadi hadadi ka atu. As soon
as the fetus starts forming, it's forbidden as camel and its גיד
gid is forbidden as גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. So both prohibitions come
at the same time. So the גמרא says okay, but one minute,
ומי מצית סברת נוהג בשליא? U'mi matzmit savrat noheig b'shilya? Can רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda really say it applies as a fetus? והתנן, V'hatnan,
the משנה Mishnah says, נוהג בשליא, noheig b'shilya, in our first משנה,
Mishnah, it applies even in the fetus. רבי יהודה אומר אינו נוהג
בשליא. Rabbi Yehuda omer eino noheig b'shilya. It doesn't apply in the
fetus. Remember because the fetus is like a piece of the mother,
it's not its independent thing, so it doesn't have a גיד gid
yet. וחלבו מותר, V'chelbo mutar, even its חלב chelev is permissible because
it's not yet it's like a limb of the mother. So you
see he says it does not apply in the שליא. shilya. הני
מילי גבי טהורה. Hani mili gabi tehora. When do we consider the
fetus a limb of the mother? Remember there was always that ambiguity.
Is it fully a limb, not fully a limb? So the גמרא
says it's not a physical statement, it's a הלכתית halachic statement. So
when are we prepared to consider it a part of the mother?
By a כשר kosher animal, that there's a point of considering it
part of the mother. רחמנא אמר כל בבהמה תאכלו Rachmana amar kol
babeheima tocheilu and the תורה Torah tells us the שחיטה shechita of
the mother works for the fetus. So there the תורה Torah is
telling us we'll let the שחיטה shechita of the mother work for
the fetus and therefore you can consider the fetus a part of
a limb of the mother. But אבל בטמאה aval bitmei'ah by a
non-kosher animal where שחיטה shechita isn't relevant, נוהג, noheig, the fetus would
be considered completely independent and therefore the גיד gid would be because
there's no הלכה halachic reason to consider it a part of the
mother. So no גיד. gid. Okay, so now the גמרא is saying
they both come at the same time because it does apply to
the fetus of a non-kosher animal. ומי מצית אמרת דתרווייהו בהדי הדדי
קאתו, umi matzis amris detravaio bahadi hadadi kavos, can you really say
they come at the same time? והתנן, vehatnan, we have this משנה
mishna again, we taught this once before. אלו טמאות הנזיר מגלח, elu
tmei'os hanazir migalei'ach, the following impurities a נזיר nazir has to shave
for, he becomes טמא, tamei, he has to start his נזירות nezirus
again. על המת כזית מן המת, al hameis ke-zayis min hameis, whether
it's a full corpse or even a כזית ke-zayis of a corpse.
וקשיא לן, vekashya lan, we asked, על כזית מן המת מגלח על
המת כולו לא כל שכן? al ke-zayis min hameis migalei'ach al hameis
kulo lo kol she-kein? If he has to shave for even a
כזית ke-zayis of a corpse, certainly on a full corpse. Why do
you bother saying it? ואמר רבי יוחנן לא נצרכה אלא לנפל. va'amar
Rabbi Yochanan lo nitzrecha ela lenefel. There are times you could have
a full corpse that נבך nebach isn't even a כזית ke-zayis because
it's a very early miscarriage, so the entire corpse is less than
a כזית. ke-zayis. שלא נתקשרו איבריו בגידים, shelo nitkashru eivarav begidin, and
it hasn't even its sinews haven't even formed. So the only reason
we bring this in is to say you see that the sinews
form later than the formation of the fetus. So even if it
applies to a fetus, they don't come at the same time. First
it begins as a fetus and it's forbidden as camel, and only
let's say, I don't know, by the sixth week does he get
the גיד gid and then it's forbidden as גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh.
So how do you have two איסורים? issurim? They don't come at
the same time. אלמא איסור טומאה קדים, alama issur tumah kadim, the
איסור issur of camel comes first. אף על גב, af al gav,
so גמרא, here's the answer, we'll end with this. אף על גב
דאיסור טומאה קדים, af al gav de'issur tumah kadim, although the prohibition
of camel came first, אתי איסור גיד חייל עליה, asi issur gid
chayal alai, the prohibition of גיד gid can take effect on top
of the איסור issur of camel. Why? שכן איסור נוהג בבני נח.
shekein issur noheig bivnei Noach. It's more strict that it applies to
בני נח. bnei Noach. Now that doesn't mean בני נח. bnei Noach.
It means it applied even to בני יעקב. bnei Yaakov. Because it
applied even before מתן תורה matan Torah according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, that gives it greater weight and allows it to take effect
on top. דיקא נמי, dayika nami, that can be inferred, דקתני אמר
רבי יהודה אבל לא מבני יעקב נאסר גיד הנשה ועדיין בהמה טמאה
מותרת להם. deketani amar Rabbi Yehuda aval lo mivnei Yaakov ne'esar gid
hanasheh va'adain beheima tmei'ah muteres lahem. Since רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
ah, it was forbidden to בני יעקב, bnei Yaakov, so now notice
the משנה mishna had no discussion of אין איסור חל על איסור.
ein issur chal al issur. The גמרא seems like it was completely
irrelevant, and רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda point was just to demonstrate that
there was a time in history when it applied to camels. So
we still say it applies to camels. But the גמרא reads it
as that's why one prohibition can take place on top of another.
Since it's more weighty in that it began even earlier, therefore it's
able to take effect on top of the prohibition of the איסור
issur of camel. We will end.